[Music]
Stanford
University okay let's uh we're going
we're entering today into the world of
quantum field Theory Quantum field
theory is of course the description of
nature as we know it with the exception
of gravity and
so practically everything that we know
with the exception of gravity imp
principle we think is explainable if
only we had the computational power to
be able to solve Quantum field theories
with uh the accuracy that would be uh
appropriate now the problem is of course
that um problems tend to be much too
complicated to solve except for some
very special problems you can understand
the hydrogen atom but by the time you
get to the to the Boron atom they're too
complicated and so forth and certainly
studying human beings as well beyond the
capacity of any Quantum field theorist
that I
know
[Music]
um and uh but
nevertheless apart from Gravity Quantum
field Theory seems to be all there is
and we're going to enter into the study
of it
today in a very very very Elementary
way we're going to study today the idea
of what is called second
quantization but before we do and second
quantization is about Quantum Fields but
we'll come to it I want to review
something first and um maybe generalize
that something a little
bit the thing that I want to study or to
remind you of or go through with you is
again the harmonic
oscillator but a new aspect of the
harmonic
oscillator a couple of new aspects of
the harmonic oscillator just so that we
have it in front of us because the
harmonic oscillator is the central
ingredient the central mathematical
structure that goes into Quantum field
Theory so we need to understand it make
sure we understand it
well but we're not going to worry about
Springs and uh and you know systems
oscillating when I speak about the
harmonic oscill oscillator I'm really
speaking about the algebra of those
little operators A+ and a
minus and the product of A+ * a minus
which is what do you
remember what is
iter it's the number operator it's the
number of the excitation so I'll remind
you now we'll go through a little bit
and I'll tell you one or two facts that
I may not have told you
about what I'm particularly allart right
so let's let's just write write down the
rules for a single harmonic for an
harmonic
oscillator a
pluses they act on states to elevate
them up to the next level there are a
minuses which take you
down at the bottom level the ground
state a minus gives you nothing it just
annihilates the state all right so a
minus is the lowering
operator and um A+ is the a raising
operator we're going to learn to call
them creation operators and Annihilation
operators what is it that they create
and annihilate as we'll see
particles uh but let's just uh use the
same not the same conventions that we've
used up till
now
and there is also A+ times a
minus that was the thing if you remember
that went into the hamiltonian if if you
remember the hamiltonian was just
basically A+ a minus what was it A+
is x + I Omega P ided by some square
root of 2
Omega a minus is the same sort of thing
with a minus sign in there and if you
multiply them together you get things
with x² uh X2 plus do I have that right
P plus no no I have it wrong
it's p plus Omega
X and if you multiply the two of them
together you get p^2 + Omega 2 x^2 plus
this extra little term that was the
ground state
energy uh and so that was that that went
into the hamiltonian A+ * a minus and we
called it the number operator it was the
thing whose igen values whose observable
values were the integer level spacing or
the integer levels of the harmonic
oscillator so I believe we called this
capital N if I
remember and it's igen values we called
little n the observable values of
it one more thing the commutation
relations of A+ and a
minus that's what made oh A+ and a minus
are Herm mission conjugates of each
other that's an important mathematical
fact but the other mathematical fact is
that the commutator of a minus with
A+ is equal to one that's what made
everything work that's what we used to
find the properties of what happens when
we act with A+ and a minus we used those
commutation
relations that was basically it that's
all that went into the harmonic OS
osor now I'm going to suppose I have
many harmonic oscillators you could just
think of them as a collection of
Springs collection of Springs or you
could think of them as the various
oscillations of a violin string or
whatever for whatever reason there
happen to be many independent systems
that are undergoing oscillation or that
can undergo oscillations possibly with
different frequency
possibly with different frequencies
where does the frequency come into all
of this the frequency well first of all
it comes in here but by the time we get
to that point over there the place where
the um the frequency came in was just
the fact that the energy is
equal H time the
frequency times this in
here there also plus a half or I'm going
to leave out the half the ground state
it's not important for us all right so
that's where the frequency came in it
came in just as telling us what the
energy for each increase of the number
operator was the
frequency together with har determine
each time we go up a
level how much energy it cost to jump
the oscillator up one level or how much
energy we might get back in some other
form form if the oscillator jumps
down if it jumps up for some reason
that's how much energy we have to pay H
bar Omega if it jumps down that's how
much energy we get and
um as I said that's the single harmonic
oscillator but now if we have many
harmonic oscillators we can label them
we could label them with an index and
I'll use the index I but I does not
stand for the square root of minus one
it's just a label which goes over all
the possible oscillators that I'm
interested in they may be a finite
number there may be an infinite number
in the examples that we'll be interested
in there are an infinite number all
right so now we get to
label the
oscillators just by putting
in well okay we have to be a little
careful over
here each oscillator think of it as an
independent system as a system which is
just an independent uh degree of
freedom and when you have independent
degrees of freedom The Operators for one
subsystem commute with the operators for
the other sub for any other subsystem
that's a rule we went through it uh two
years ago or a year ago whenever it was
The Operators describing system a and
the operators for describing system B if
a and b are truly independent systems
they commute with each other why because
to not commute would tell you that you
cannot measure them independently if you
can't measure them independently they're
not independent
systems so presumably if you had two
Springs you could take one off with over
there and the other one way off over
there and there's no reason why they
should influence each other their
operators everything about them
commutes and so we can write the
following
that let's write out all the commutation
relations because they're
important let's forget this for the
moment let's first
take the commutation relations of the
lowering
operators I with
J the first oscillator with the 14th
oscillator okay
let's well first of all if I is not
equal to J they're talking about
different oscillators if we're talking
about different oscillators they must
commute but if we're talking about the
same oscillator then the commutator
should be exactly the same as it was for
the single oscillator case namely
one so how do we write that we write
write that by putting the chronica Delta
over here all that means oh so now zero
sorry zero Annihilation operators all
commute with each
other uh even for a single oscillator
the annihilation operator commutes with
itself because everything commutes with
itself same thing for the creation
operators or the raising operator
ators but now here is what I wanted to
say a moment ago if I take the
annihilation operator and take its
commutator with a creation
operator then if I is not J we're
talking about two different oscillators
they don't know about each other they
don't talk to each other uh or at least
they they may talk to each other but
they uh are independent of each other
and the commutator must be zero on the
other hand if it's the same oscillator
that we're talking about then the
commutator must be
one so this is equal to Delta i
j this is the algebra of The Operators
of many harmonic
oscillators you need to know
that and one more thing What's the total
energy the total energy is just the sum
of the energy of all the
oscillators so let's write
that the total energy which we can take
to be the hamiltonian is the sum over
all
I all the oscillators the first
oscillator the second oscillator
of Omega I'll include the H bar for the
moment I'll probably forget about it
before the night is over Omega but which
Omega each oscillator may have a
different frequency so each oscillator
the contribution of the I oscillator is
proportional to the frequency of the I
oscill dat times n
subai we're going to give a name to
insabi
now we're going to call
in or insabi but in we're going to call
them occupation
numbers uh not occupation like what's
your occupation but
occupation in the sense of you are
sitting there occupying some
space okay
all right these are the occupation
numbers it's just a name for the moment
what is it that's doing the occupying
well we'll find out but this says that
each oscillator has an energy
proportional to its occupation number
times Omega times its frequency with the
H bar being there there is the extra
half of ground state energy I want to
ignore it it's it's of no interest plays
no role it's just an additive constant
additive constants in energy are don't
make any
difference okay that's the whole theory
if you like well not quite not quite now
how do we label States if we have many
oscillators if we have one if we have
one oscillator we can label a complete
basis of States just
by the
level or the occupation number of the
oscillator remember we have all these
states n equals z which is the ground
state which we sometimes just call O Nal
1 which we call 1 Nal 2 and so forth and
so
on we label the states by the occupation
number that's a state what if we have
many oscillators and I now imagine that
I lay them out there are many oscillator
here's the first one over here second
one over here third one over here fourth
one over here I = 1 I = 2 and so
forth then in order to specify a state I
have to specify the occupation number or
one way of specifying a complete basis
of
States one way of specifying a basis of
states is to label was to write down the
occupation number of each
oscillator how many quanta or how many
units of energy are there so to
speak in the first oscillator I'm going
to call the first oscillator n no
N1 N1
N2 and
three if there's a finite number of
oscillators it terminates if there's an
infinite number it doesn't do you know
any situations where uh at least
mathematically there's an infinite
number of
oscillators what's that the
Contin well if you yeah um an example
would be an a Very idealized
mathematical violin string a violin
string has any number of harmonics
everyone can oscillate with a different
frequency that's a mathematically
idealized uh of course the real violin
string is made of atoms and there aren't
really that many possibilities but
violin string would be a mathematically
ideal idealized violin string would have
an infinite number of oscillators but of
course the very very high in very high I
would correspond to extremely rapid uh
frequencies and
really because of the atomic structure
of the uh violin string it really
doesn't have that many
oscillators
um but that's an example mathematically
of infinitely many and we're going to be
interested in that
case okay let's talk about ah let's come
over to another Blackboard over here
we're going to little more a little more
oscillation a little more oscillator
mathema
I I told you in the
originally
that if you
act with the creation operator or the
I'm going to call it I'll slip into
calling it The Creation operator with a
creation operator you increase n by one
unit well that's not quite right not if
we normalize the states in the usual way
the usual way to normalize a family of
States they're orthogonal to each other
for different in why are they orthogonal
to each other because they have a
different observably different number of
in so states with different values of an
igen value or orthogonal so the usual
normalization would be that the inner
product of n with m is Delta n m or not
in other words each state
NN is equal to
1 n
m is equal to zero for n not equal to M
they're
orthogonal for n equal to n we normally
would take them to be normalized States
that's standard quantum mechanical uh
notation
procedure with that notation in other
words each one of these states is of
unit length
each one of these states is of unit
length but with that notation A Plus on
N does not give n+ one it gives a
numerical coefficient in front and
numerical
coefficient is the square root of n+
one let me prove that for you
let's see if we can prove
it ah we can do it over
here okay
let's not put the answer
in let's just call this some numerical
coefficient and we don't know what it is
yet we don't know what it is yet it's
some CN and we're going to try to figure
out what it is what's our tool our tool
is the commutation relations for the
oscill there a single oscillator now not
multiple
oscillators
okay let's write this is a this is a k
vector equation let's write the
corresponding bra vector equation when
you write when you go from a k
vector equation to a bra vector equation
what do you do with the
operators the ks go to braas what about
the
operators Herm Mission conjugate Herm
Mission conjugate Herm Mission
conjugate all right the her Mission
conjugate of A+ is a minus so another
way to write the same
fact
is the Herm Mission
conjugate on the bra Vector
n is equal to CN I'm assuming that CN is
real we can do the complex case it
doesn't matter uh we can it's it's okay
to think of CN as real I don't uh it
doesn't it doesn't matter but let's let
it be real if it wasn't real then we
would want the complex conjugate but we
can choose it to be real and then n +
one that's the exact same equation
except bras kets go to bras operators go
to their her Mission conjugate and
numbers go to their complex conjugate
but I'm taking C to be equal to a real
number
okay now here's what we're going to
do we're going to put this equation next
to we're going to take the inner product
of this equation with this equation with
the bottom one with the top one let's
write it out
N A
minus
A+ n that's what happens if you take the
inner product of the left side here with
the right side here and that's going to
equal CN
sared times the inner product of this
Vector with this Vector but what's the
inner product of this with
this one one every one of these vectors
is normalized to one so it's just
one so now we have a tool to figure out
what CN is all right all we have to do
is juggle the a pluses and a minuses in
a clever
way how do we want to what do we want to
do I think I erased an equation over
here I should have written yeah let's
let's write down the guiding equation
over here or over
here
n on the nth
state is equal to little n on the nth
State why is that
true come
on definition of being an igen Vector
little n is the igen vector of big n big
n n acts on the igen state with igen
value n to give little n that's the
definition of an igen Vector question
yes um I don't see why the in product of
n plus1 n plus1 is one because I've used
the rule but we hav normalized yet no no
no no now I've assumed they
normalized I'm assuming now that the N
vectors are
normalized and
having okay goad no no I've I have put
the ambiguity into the C's right I may
assume that they're normalized and then
seek to got it right yeah okay good all
right
so B is nothing but a plus a minus so
let's put that
here A+ A minus
that's almost what I have here A plus I
don't have A+ a minus I have a minus A+
but what I know is what a plus a minus
does what can I
do what's that
operation
commute commute and here is our
commutator the commutator is one so what
that
says is that this same thing is equal to
n a + a
minus + one that's the commutated term
n okay now I'm in good shape because I
know what a plus a minus does when it
acts on N it just multiplies by little
n so all of this just gives
me n +
1 times the inner product of n with
itself which is what
1 so there we have it cn2 is equal to n
+ 1 and therefore CN is the square root
of n +
1 we now
know what the creation operator does in
all of its Glory
it increases
the occupation number by one and it
multiplies by the number Square Ro TK of
n +
1 we can get rid of the rest of this we
don't need it anymore
next what about a minus on
N well you go through essentially the
same little game you can do it yourself
it doesn't take uh it's not very hard
this time you don't even have to do any
commutator they'll wind up in the right
order and what you'll find out is that
this is equal to the square root of n *
nus1 in other words it takes you down a
level but multiplies by the square root
of n notice that this one yeah okay
that's that's that's what you
find once you know this formula here you
don't have to worry about the fact of
what happens when a minus hits the
bottom
level when a minus hits the bottom level
the bottom level is n equals z you get
zero so this equation as it stands now
encodes the fact that the lowering
operator annihilates or kills or gives
zero when it acts on the ground state
that's just the square square root of n
here so this
is more
oscillator stuff that I assume that
durra was uh was responsible
for now we know I think everything we
need to know about how monic oscillators
at least for the
moment and that was just a mathematical
interlude if you like uh to uh so that
we'd have it in front of us when we need
it let's put it up on
top any questions about harmonic
oscillators or multiple harmonic
oscillators oh
oh one thing
what
happens here's a particular vector or a
particular state which has a certain set
of occupation numbers let's hit it with
a creation operator for the
I oscillator we're going to the I
oscillator and we're applying one unit
of creation to it or one unit of
elevation what does it do well it goes
over to the I slot If This Were Three if
I was three it would go over to this
slot and it increases the occupation
number by one
unit but only for the particular I that
we wrote down here so if we go to the
seventh oscillator and we apply the
creation operator it increases the
seventh oscillator level it does not
increase the sixth one it doesn't
increase the fifth one you know there's
an oscillator over there it's over there
and uh it's not to be confused with
anybody else and
so what this does is it leaves all the
other ones alone let's say I is out here
somewhere n one n two dot dot dot until
we get up to the I place and then it
gives us ni I + one and
then beyond that nothing but that's this
is not quite right this is not quite
right because it fails to take into
account the square root of n + 1 so what
we have actually have to write
what am I
writing I'm I'm writing nonsense n i
equals N1 dot dot dot ni + 1 dot dot dot
but we have to put in a square root of
Ni I + 1 so in other words it works
exactly the same as a single oscillator
with all the other ones just being
bystanders
which Play No role when you hit it with
the I oscillator if you hit it with the
J oscillator another some other
occupation number would get
increased likewise for the lowering
operators or the annihilation operators
same kind of uh understanding so as I
said that uh that's what we need to know
about
oscillators now we're going to come to
Quantum Fields Real genuine Quantum
Fields but but in a very simple context
non-relativistic quantum mechanics
ordinary quantum
mechanics not relativity yet we're not
doing special relativity just ordinary
quantum
mechanics in ordinary quantum
mechanics there's some kind of funny
connection between particles and Fields
particles are described by wave
functions wave functions are functions
of position they sort of look like
Fields what are Fields field Feld are
things uh degrees of freedom which
depend on position and on time in
particular but let's just say position
for the moment let's freeze time fields
are functions of
position the wave function of a particle
is a function of
position and so you might think that's
all there is to it that's the connection
between particles and Fields but it's
not it's not let me or at least it's
only a very tiny part of it
and in fact not the real
idea right up
here so I of X so I of X is the wave
function of one particle where X is the
position of that particle X could stand
for X Y and Z of course it doesn't
necessarily stand for just X but s is a
function of
X but what is it it's not an observable
quantity it's the state Vector it's the
state Vector in the position
representation it's not unobservable you
don't do experiments to measure the wave
function of a particle you do
experiments to measure the position of a
particle or the momentum of a particle
or the angular momentum of a particle
but not the state of a particle you
don't measure that's not a measurable
thing it's a thing which tells you a
great deal about the probabilities of
various measurements but it itself is
not unobservable
so that's the first
thing
not an
observable next
fact if we have several
particles then s is not a function of
one position it's a function of all the
positions I'm going to I'm going to I
want to um EXA aate a not notation a
little bit I want to make this a small
sigh a lowercase
sigh and it's a wave
function if I have two particles let's
call them X and Y again not the x
coordinate and the y-coordinate of space
but just the coordinates of two
particles then um the wave function is a
function of two positions
all right function of several positions
in fact it's a function of the of the
position of all
particles third fact what was the third
fact
ah the third fact is given a wave
function which may depend on X1 through
some number whatever
X15 15 particles
it's the description of a fixed number
of
particles we describe 15 particles with
a 15 particle wave
function fixed number of
particles that is not the idea of a
Quantum field by contrast Now I'll Tell
You by contrast what a Quantum field is
and in many respects it's everything
that this is not although we tend to use
the same notation for it and it's
closely
related okay first of
all a Quantum field this is a w these
are wave functions and they represent
State
vectors capital
P is different number one it's an
observable it's a thing you can
measure let's just think for a moment
what is a Quantum field really going to
be in when we get to the real thing real
qu you know more complicated uh serious
Quantum field Theory it's going to be
things like the electromagnetic
field it's going to be the quantum
mechanical electromagnetic field the
electromagnetic field is most certainly
an
observable we observe
it and uh so first of all whatever sigh
is it is an observ
able number
two s is a function of only one
coordinate oh incidentally the fact that
it's an observable means that it's an
operator it means that it's an operator
in the space of States it's not itself a
state it is a operator that must be if
it's going to be an observable number
two it's a function of only one
coordinate of one
position function of
one three Vector so to
speak and
finally it
describes systems of any number of
particles any number of particles
in other words it's capable of
describing systems where particle
numbers can change even where particle
numbers can change how can particle
numbers change well if we were thinking
about the electromagnetic field and we
remember that electromagnetic field is
photons every time electromagnetic field
is radiated it changes the number of
photons so whatever s is it's a
description it's an observable it's an
operator it's a function of one position
and it
represents the quantum mechanics of any
number of particles not a fixed number
of
particles that's number
one I want I don't want to go too fast
because this is um tricky stuff yeah so
when you say function of one position
you mean the position
X where X can vary X can
vary yes X can vary but it's a function
of Only One X oh
boy it's a function of Only One X but
that doesn't mean it's a function of X
when X is five it means it's a function
of x x can be anything but it's not a
function of X1 X2 and
X3 I keep telling you why
you mean why why not
y it's just a function of one coordinate
one coordinate in real world means three
coordinates means X Y and Z but that's
not what that Y is that's no no that's
not what that Y is that why two
particles one is named X the other is
named
y why cuz who's on first that's why so
that's really just a special special
case of
y you got two parles in sxy you got 15
particles in s that's right okay right Y
is just X2 X is X1 right and one and two
label two different
particles right how do these uh
transform to each other how do you
explain one in terms of the other we're
going do that that's the
whole that's the whole
point all I laid out for you the big
contrast and now we want to know what's
the connection between them it's going
to take a little while but it's
not different kind of particles no same
kind of
particles same kind of
particles and in particular bons will
come to firion
later we'll come to firion later yes
this is the theory of
bons every everything we're doing
tonight will be
bans excuse me had a question back on
the left board about the what's that the
what a question on the left hand board
about the harmonic oscillators is the uh
assumption about the independence of the
different operators exact or
approximately correct exact okay so for
example I would not be used to index the
electrons in an atom say it again I
would not be using yeah the subscript
that wouldn't be used to index I could
be
labeling the states of an electron in an
atom now you got to be
careful um if the electrons are
interacting then it's more complicated
but if you just had non-interacting
electrons in an atom I would be labeling
the states of the atom okay but we're
going to come to
that yeah let's come through it right
now let's go back the Single part
particle quantum
mechanics this is the theory of many
particles well it could be the theory of
no particles it could be the theory of
one particle it could be the theory of
two particles variable number of
particles let's go back to the theory of
just one
particle okay and for Simplicity I'm
going to take a particular example a
particle in a
box the potential energy is such that
the particle can't get out out of the
box Just One Direction of space uh
although nothing I'm saying is going to
depend on that this is a Bo On In A Box
a Bo on in a moment for the moment it
doesn't matter if there's only one of
them it doesn't matter if there's one of
them there's no
question of whether um there's an
exclusion principle or not right so one
of them doesn't
matter let's think about the energy igen
states
of a particle in a
box they're wave
functions for example the lowest energy
wave
function will be the smoothest wave
function that satisfies the Schrodinger
equation and it'll typically look
something like that it'll be a sign
function that just barely fits in the
box that fits in the box from one end to
the
other and that's a wave function it's a
wave function in the sense of this one
over
here let's give it a name let's call it
s one of
X this should be little
s just make sure it's little
s it's just the wave function of a one
particle system in a box S one of X what
does the one represent just that it's
the first energy level the lowest energy
level
what about the next energy level the
next energy level is some other wave
function and as you go up in energy the
wave functions tend to tend to be more
variable the next one would have a node
like
that we can call that side 2 of
X I'm using a funny
notation
uh the index here is not the the number
of nodes it's one more than the number
of nodes number of nodes in the box so
the next one would be SI 2 of
X would have a higher
energy and so forth and so on now these
the ones and the twos here do not
represent go down the line s i of
X now this I is will be the same as this
I
eventually but at the moment they're two
different things in this case it's
labeling oscillators in this case it's
labeling State vectors of one particle
in a box just one
particle each one has an
energy uh I won't write down what the
energy is other than to remind you that
each each of these wave functions does
have an energy
okay everybody all right with that one
particle wave functions
now let's imagine now that we have many
particles we have many particles of an
undetermined
number but some number of
them with in state
one some number of particles in the Box
occupying State one some number of
particles occupying state two some
number of particles occupying state
three and so
forth that is a pretty good
description of a wide class or a basis
of states in fact if I
know uh that is a basis of States saying
how many particles occupy each energy
level okay so let's write that down now
here's a family of
states number of
particles in state
one number of particles in state
two number of particles in state three
oh boy Deja
Vu where is uh ah here it is over here
absolutely identical to the way I
labeled the states of Harmon of a
multiple harmonic oscillator system
now of course the
um there are infinitely many possible
States in here of arbitrary uh
wavelength arbitrarily small wavelength
and that's the reason why we need to
study any number of oscillators up to
Infinity okay so here is a
parallel between you wouldn't want to do
this for you couldn't do this for Fons
for Fons you can either have no particle
in a with a particular state or one
particle never
two okay can't put two so in writing
down the idea that you can have any
number of particles in the first state
any number in the second state any
number in the third state we're assuming
for the begin with that we're talking
about
bons okay but notice there's complete
parallel here because there's a complete
parallel it means we can invent this is
an invention out of the head operators
which do exactly the same thing
as the creation and Annihilation
operators do now they literally create
particles for
example a
+1 on N1 dot dot
dot gives me Square < TK of n + 1 N1 + 1
* N1 + one and two and three and so
forth it increases the number of
particles in the first state whatever it
was it adds one and multiplies by the
standard square
root why does it multiplied by the
standard square root that's a definition
but it's a definition which is very
cleverly
chosen among other things so that we can
use all the apparatus that we have about
oscillators which is very helpful as
we'll
see likewise with the annihilation
operator now I'll call him creation and
Annihilation operators they create and
annihilate or remove particles from the
system okay that's the basic idea of
creation and Annihilation
operators question yeah on your your Top
Line there N1 N2 N3 I thought N1 and N2
were the quantum
States one two and three are the quantum
States N1 N2 and N3 are the number of
part particles in that
state 1 2 and three
are 1 2 and three up to I or man past
okay so this is tricky there's a lot of
notation but the
notation is it's not hard it's just a
bit to
remember uh so I'm going slow for that
reason and repeating
myself question please what what's the
physical meaning in this environment of
of that square
root
A+ a minus on
N is equal to
n * in
right well A+ is awful a lot like a
minus so it better be that A+ and a
minus are somehow square roots of n but
we can do better than that let's see how
can we do better than that
uh let's use the commutation relations
no okay let's suppose we didn't know
this let's suppose we didn't know this
but we did know about the square roots
of
n okay let's suppose we didn't know we
knew about the square roots of
n
okay let's use our commutation relations
to write this as a minus A+
Plus on N minus one I
think
yes a minus A+ is equal to A+ a
minus plus
one plus one right h
oneus
oneus well let's see A+ a minus A+ - A
plus a minus is equal to
so +
one no you right I was right
right I had it right if it doesn't work
out we'll change
it
okay now what does a Plus on N do
according to assumption it gives you
square < TK of n +
1 * n + 1
okay that's this that's over here but we
still have to multiply by a minus and
then we have another minus n that's what
we have here
right okay this is just a number square
root of n plus1 let's put it over here
square of n +
1 what does a minus do when it acts on
squ < T of n+ one oh sorry on n+
one no I think yeah it gives us in but
what's the numerical
number squ root of n+ 1 right so we get
two square roots of n + 1 which gives
what n +
1 time n -1 * n which is just good old
[Music]
n time n in other words those square
roots of n are there to ensure that this
Vector is really an Vector of A+ a minus
and roughly speaking very roughly A+ and
a minus are of the same order of
magnitude one is uh P plus iix the other
is p minus IX same order of magnitude
and since Al together they add up or
they multiply together to give you
n each one is roughly the square root of
n question yeah so um okay sort of to
find A+ and a minus you have no way to
find them but you can find sort of
various properties that they have like
commutation property yeah so but we
don't have a definition out of it other
than kind of Its Behavior we're making
it up okay we're def we're Define we're
not making up randomly but we're
defining things and then we're going to
see how they work forgive me I my
question was I understand when you apply
A+ you create a particle
mhm that a very tangible thing I didn't
understand what does it square root do
in a tangible sense that's my
question
well but maybe nothing sometimes
mathematics is just mathematics I mean
sometimes uh it's like you for ordinary
quad mechanics you have to normalize the
wave function you only have one particle
it's the same thing here
okay right why does the particle
disappear why doesn't it become
different state
what when you do Aus why does it
disappear why do why doesn't it become a
different that's the definition of a
minus you can't ask why about a
definition I Define a minus so that it
decreases the number of particles okay
definition mathematics we make
definitions and then we find the
consequences of them so the question is
why is it a useful definition
well it's a useful definition because we
want to explore systems of various
numbers of particles in fact we want to
explore systems where the number of
particles can
change for example we might radiate a
photon how would we go about
mathematically indicating that we
created a photon we take the state and
we hit it with a cre Photon creation
operator or a photon might be absorbed
a atom might absorb a photon how do we
write the fact or how do we express the
fact that a photon has the photon has
disappeared we express it by saying an
Annihilation operator has acted so the
purpose of all of this is not only to be
able to study systems of arbitrary
number of particles but even to be able
to study systems of variable number of
particles
okay question mhm so here's what I think
you're doing what you're doing is you're
defining these operators how they act on
I vectors yeah and since item vectors
form a basis yeah that tells us how they
act on all vectors okay I got that part
right on okay now we've got this
definition of a plus and a minus we
haven't shown but one assumes that one
can show that you have a commutation uh
relationships that you've got up there
yeah with these definitions it will will
follow that these operators have the
same commutation there right in other
words the system of a variable number of
particles here can be represented just
as a system of harmonic
oscillators and an oscillator for each
state for each single particle state for
each single particle wave function an
oscillator and the occupation number of
that oscillator is the number of
particles that are occupying ing that
particular state so the terminology is
well chosen occupation now we know what
it means it's not you occupying your
seat it's a particle occupying a state
and a bon in
particular these are creation and
Annihilation operators for
particles how would you label what's the
vacuum in this language
the
vacuum well first of all it's the state
which is annihilated by all of the
annihilation operators it's the state
which when you try to
lower any occupation number there's
nothing there nothing to lower so the
state becomes zero but the vacuum is
simply the state with zero occupation
ation number in
every state it has the property that all
the occupation numbers are zero and it
has the property that any one of the a
minuses gives zero when it
acts so so the ground state is
unoccupied as well ground state is
unoccupied right but it was occupied you
still couldn't lower it if we're
occupied you can lower it the ground
state no the ground state is not
occupied you can't
occupy that didn't make
sense the ground state in the vacuum are
the same
thing
sorry
right let's while we're at it let's
write an expression which we can now do
for the energy of the
system we in order to write an
expression for the energy of the system
we need to know the energy of each one
of these wave functions each wave
function has associated with it an
energy igen value what should we call
them the energies we could call them e
couldn't
we I'm going to call them Omega or
actually har bar Omega but let's just
call the energy level of the I let's
kill har bar forget har bar because I've
already forgotten
it and just say the
energy of a particle in the first state
would be Omega
1 the energy of a particle in the second
state would be Omega
2 and so forth the energy of a particle
in the I state would be Omega
I let's write an expression in terms of
creation and annihilation operators for
the energy of the whole
system this is
easy the energy of the whole system is
first of
all the energy of all of the particles
in the first state so that's the number
of particles in the first
state n one times the energy that's
associated with particle in the first
state Omega
1 plus the number of particles in the
second state times Omega 2 plus and so
forth and so on so it's the
sum
of N subi Omega subi now that's a true
statement
but I want to write it as an operator
statement these ns are igen values but
they're igen values of the number
operator so we can really write this in
operator form by saying it's the sum of
all the states single particle states of
Omega I times the occupation number of
the I
State and what is the occupation number
of the I State a dagger i a a
I notice that each one of these is just
basically the oscillator formula this is
just the oscillator formula there would
be an har bar in here put an H bar if
you like uh this is just the oscillator
formula but now it's summed over all the
possible uh States here and you can
think of it two ways you can think of it
somehow the system of particles is
equivalent to oscillation
and those are just the oscillator
energies or you can say it's just the
sum of the energy of all the
particles the number of particles in the
first mode first state times the energy
of the first state plus the second state
times the energy of the second state and
so forth and it comes out to the same
thing yeah question what is
ai ai a minus I sorry okay good so so a
what is a here creation oh sorry
yeah okay
good in many contexts I'm sorry in many
contexts once you go to Quantum field
Theory which is what we're doing now A+
just becomes a dagger and a minus just
becomes
a well I I'll try to stick with the same
notation I don't want to change
notations
now okay
so let's let just uh think for a minute
what are we
doing we're inventing some kind of
object which is a which is a bunch of
oscillators on the other hand the violin
string is a bunch of oscillators the
violin string is a field if you look at
radiation in a cavity radiation bouncing
between mirrors it's a bunch of
oscillators people speak I mean this
goes back from long before quantum
mechanics speak about radiation as a
collection of oscillators
radiation oscillators long before
quantum
mechanics and so we're beginning to
build up from thinking about ordinary
particles we're beginning to build up an
idea of collections of
particles as harmonic
oscillators and soon enough we're going
to see the connection with
Fields okay uh if there are no more
questions uh maybe we'll take a five
minute break because
uh I need to stop for a few
minutes and uh organize your
thoughts and we'll field a few questions
before we go
on is what honi hamiltonian that is the
hamiltonian that is the
hamiltonian we're going to find other
very elegant ways to write
it but that is the hamiltoni right
guess I'll be collecting
okay yeah
um okay I don't want to I want to be
able to remember where I left off
okay
good what do you do with them you put
them on
the I
know yeah I assume he puts them up I
don't know don't know put
I thought that was the idea but I don't
remember yeah okay
do those normalization factors apply to
the harmonic what's that those
normalization factors n n one yeah they
app seems like exactly the same
yeah what's
that no that has nothing to do with it
no the energy levels no it's not the
energy levels of the single particles in
the boxes which are which are evenly
spaced it's the energy levels of no
particle one particle two particle three
particles which are evenly spaced for
each oscillator
right single
parle yes
yeah
no no we're not talking about particles
which are moving in a potential which is
an oscillator you could you could think
of a lot of particles in a potential of
an ill Ator then you would have two
kinds of oscillators the particles would
be oscillators and the creation and
Annihilation operators would be
oscillators but now we're just talking
about um
any collection of single particle States
single particle States is just what you
would have thought about were you're
just thinking about one particle quantum
mechanics but now since we can talk
about any number of particles we can um
we can generalize in this way
okay
okay let's uh let's get
back are there some questions because uh
I don't want to go too
fast I know that there's a lot of little
indices and little pieces and nuts and
bolts here which if we go fast they'll
slip out of your head and uh they slip
out of my head from time to time and
uh
yes decomposition M for
sure for a decomposition you're going to
have arbitrary amplitudes to De the
A's the A's are the complex amplitudes
of Foria
coefficients right we'll come to
that yes it's deeply
related with Foria with Foria analysis
absolutely are we assuming that all the
partic have the same same energy same
energy no no no no no no no in the if
they're in the first state they have
energy one right all the particles which
are in the first state have the same
energy yeah all the particles in the
second state have the same energy as
each other but not as the ones in the
first
state so you know I'm but they interact
with each other well okay for the moment
we're talking about particles that don't
interact for the moment we're talking
about particles which simply don't
interact with each
other that's the starting
point uh later we have to ask what kind
of things uh do we have to do to get the
particles to interact what Georgia was
saying is that if particles really
interacted with each other the energies
wouldn't really be additive there
wouldn't just be the energy of particle
1 plus the energy of particle 2 there
would be the energy of particle 1 plus
the energy of particle two plus any kind
of potential energy between them for
example so it right so that's that's
correct for the moment we're talking
about free particles free particles
means particles which don't interact
with each
other
uh okay now we come no qu no other
question question yes so in non ristic
Quantum field Theory there's still a
half B on in the ground state yes but it
doesn't play it doesn't do anything it's
just Zero Point Energy and um why
doesn't Zero Point Energy why is it
irrelevant for everything well if you
think what does energy is
hamiltonian what happens if you add a
constant a number to a hamiltonian well
a number commutes with everything and if
you remember what the hamiltonian does
for you is it provides a method of
getting equations of motion the time
dependence of something is related to
the commutator of that thing with a
hamiltonian constants do nothing they
commute with
everything another way of saying it is
in keeping track of energies the only
thing that really counts is energy
differences not the so you can throw
away that ground state energy uh
except for certain very special purposes
that uh that are not going to concern us
right
now okay Quantum
Fields a field is a function of space
it's not a function of two points of
space or three points of space so it's
not like the wave function of a many
particle system it's a thing which only
depends on one coordinate it's also an
operator why because it's an observable
You observe Fields you measure
them what was the third point about
uh well I don't remember but um any yeah
and somehow somehow has to do with your
ability to change the number of
particles okay so I'm what we're going
to do is I'm going to give you the rule
for the quantum field of this system of
particles and then we're going to
explore how it works if you ask ask me
prematurely why that's the definition
well it won't work it won't work the
best thing to do sometimes it's just
best
to follow the definition and I won't I
promise you we won't go too far before
you start to see why it works and why
it's interesting and why why that's the
definition but it's better not to try to
um to Intuit it out from the
beginning why this is the particular
definition
rather get used to it and familiar with
it then in a short amount of time you'll
understand why that's the thing to
do the definitions the value of the
definitions depends on their
utility all right on what you can do
with them and I I might say this to
begin with Quantum field Theory at least
in the way we're thinking about it here
among other things is a bookkeeping
device it's a bookkeeping device for
keeping track
of many particles for keeping track of
the quantum mechanics of particles which
come and go change their state even
disappear and reappear whatever it's a
kind of bookkeeping device whenever you
have operators like this you're doing
bookkeeping it's a little more than that
because you can actually measure these
fields the things when they go by you
you feel them they have an effect on you
but for the moment we can just think of
it as
bookkeeping and whether a definition is
a useful definition or not depends on
what you try to do with it I can tell
you with Quantum Fields you can do a
lot yeah could you take a minute or two
to say just a little bit about the
history of quantum field Theory when it
was developed to developed
it
um
well we go way way back we can start
with the question of who invented field
Theory right who invented field Theory
anybody know who invented field Theory I
suppose it was
Faraday with the electric and magnetic
field so I think probably the idea can
best be uh the the original history
started with I think with Faraday
Maxwell invented field equations Faraday
didn't have field equations he just had
a feeli for the fields field for the
fields and was able to visualize them
Maxwell wrote down as far as I know well
it's probably not true that he was the
first one to write down a wave equation
wave equations waves of water waves of
other things but I think it can fairly
be said that Maxwell wrote down the
first modern version of field Theory but
it was classical field
Theory
um the need to quantize fields or the
need to do something involving harar
goes back to
plunk
plunk well it goes back before
plunk uh we have not talked we will
eventually talk about what is called the
ultraviolet
catastrophe won't talk about it now but
uh plunk realized that uh that classical
field Theory would not be adequate for
studying thermodynamics of radiation
introduced Plank's constant and in the
process
uh basically said some things about
harmonic
oscillators which were more or less
correct he didn't realize that the
radiation field itself was made out of
oscillators or photons as we Quant of
the field he was thinking about the
oscillators in the walls of a cavity
namely the atoms which he thought of
envisioned as literally oscillators
little oscillating charges
and um his application of Plank's
constant and this he didn't have this
mathematics but the idea that the energy
levels were integer spaced he wrongly
thought that that had to do with the um
with the oscillators in the walls of the
of the cavity it was Einstein who first
um understood that the that the
quantization of
oscillations had to do with the electr
magnetic field with Maxwell's
electromagnetic field so as with almost
everything else it was Einstein who uh
had the first inklings of
this but then
later it was Heisenberg poy der was the
Der was the person who really put it
together in the form we're talking
about
uh and that was
basically around
1929 around 1929 a lot of these ideas uh
first really surfaced but um you know as
usual Einstein uh had really did have
all the ideas and
uh um although he hadn't articulated
them in in exactly the modern
form after
that the whole history but uh not for
tonight not for tonight um this notion
of particles or variable number of
particles as harmonic oscillators that's
a good question who was the first
one I'm guessing der again but I'm not
sure that he was the first one to
identify particle creation and
Annihilation as a form of um harmonic
oscillated
mathematics I would guess it was dur
around
1930 what was the first major problem
that they could solve that hadn't been
solved before the first major problem
was the problem of the ultraviolet
catastrophe of
uh of
um or basically why radiation was
quantized Einstein knew radiation was
quantized okay he knew that radiation
came in photons but he didn't have a
mathematical way to think about it
uh the first major problem that was
solved was a formal mathematical quantum
mechanics that was consistent with the
rest of quantum mechanics that included
the idea that radiation came in
photons that radiation came so far we
have never even talked about what a
photon is we're getting close we're
getting close a photon has something to
do with the electromagnetic
field and it's a unit of energy
it's like these occupation
numbers okay the things which occupy the
occupation numbers are
Quant if the particles we're talking
about are the Quant of the
electromagnetic field they're called
photons so that's where we're going
we're really getting close to talking
about what a photon
is or what a Quantum of a field is in
fact right now we're going to in ruce
the notion of a Quantum
field the simplest version of
it I'm going to give it to you as a
definition and we're going to see what
it does and how it
works okay so s is a Quantum
field and I'm going again because it's a
Quantum field it's an operator it's
something you can measure
I'm going to call it capital
P it's an operator but it's an operator
which depends on position so it's not a
single operator it's an operator for
each position for each position a
separate operator it acts on a space of
states the space of States what is the
space of states the space of
states where is it we erased it
well the space of
states and one and
two
incidentally this is called Fox space f
f was a Russian physicist I don't I
doubt very much that he was the first
one to use this but um he wasn't but it
got named after him for the usual
reasons that PE get things get named
after people namely no reason
um okay the quantum field s of X this
just a very short
definition it's equal to the sum over
all
of the single particle wave functions
sum over I a contribution for each one
of these
states so it's a sum of
I it contains s i of
X the single particle wave function
these are things like SS and cosiness SS
and cosiness of different uh of
different wave number of different uh
wavelength that's what goes there and
what multiplies it the
coefficients the coefficients are the
creation and Annihilation operators in
this case the annihilation
operators I now somebody asked me if any
of of this has to do with Foria
analysis if the size are moment what
what the if the size were momentum Ian
states that means they're SS and
cosiness then these operators a minus
would look would resemble very closely
the coefficients that occur in Foria
analysis that is they are the quantum
version of the Foria
coefficients when you expand the thing
in SS and cosiness now it might not be
signs and cosiness it's whatever the uh
the orthonormal family of states of
single particle States
is that's it that's the definition of a
Quantum field the simplest the simplest
example what's
that Does it include the side there
these size are just numbers now in fact
there's a separate number for each
position s of X are just classical just
functions so if I want to know what the
quantum field is at xals 0 I plug in
xals 0 here if I want to know what it is
at xal the square root of Pi I put in
the square root of Pi here so it's a
it's a whole set of function sorry it's
a whole set of operators one for each
position in space that's a lot of
operators
one for each position in space why so
rich why are there so many operators the
reason is because we're trying to to
study a system where there can be any
number of particles that's a lot of
States a lot of States a lot of
operators just because the number of
particles is totally unbounded in this
uh
idea okay so there's an operator at each
position this X and this x are the same
the size are different this is an oper
Ator this is just a a function a
function of
position the operator is in here that's
where the operator is
okay there
is the complex conjugate or the Herm
Mission
conjugate this an operator it's not a um
uh a number but it has a Herm Mission
conjugate it's exactly the same thing
except that we put creation operators
there and Si star
here these Quantum fields are not her
Mission and not her Mission because the
creation and Annihilation operators are
not her Mission and so they're not
really
observables but if you add Sai and S
star a s dagger or you subtract them you
can make Herm Mission combination out of
them and those really are things that
you could observe in the
laboratory uh just because they're Herm
Mission
operators now we're going to explore
these we're going to explore these
objects we're going to go
slow but the first thing I want to show
you is what the action of s is s of x
capital S of X when it hits the
vacuum what does it
do when you apply it to the
vacuum uh let's take side dagger we'll
take side dagger incidentally what does
side do when it hits the
vacuum it kills it it annihilates it why
because it's only got Annihilation
operators in
it side dagger however has creation
operators it creates a particle each
term in here creates a particle it
doesn't create a lot of particles it
creates a superposition of particles
but one particle in a superposition of
States so let's see if we can figure out
what it
does when it hits the vacuum okay so
here's what we're going to
do let's take single particle quantum
mechanics one particle quantum mechanics
to begin with in other words forget all
this fancy stuff with oscillators just
good old quantum mechanics of a single
particle there's a complete set of
states the complete set of states are
the position
states let's see how do I want to write
this
okay states which are located where the
particle is located at position X
they're a complete set of states that
means they're a complete basis of states
and that
means that you can if you sum over all
positions or integrate over all
positions I'll use a I I'll keep it
simple I'll imagine summing over
positions but we may have to do an
integral if we sum over all positions
what do we get on the right hand
side one one the unit
operator that's a general rule for any
basis of
States okay
now let's see I just trying to remember
which way I did
this that's a true statement but was
what I actually wanted was a different
statement it is a true statement but
what I actually wanted was
this
statement some of
i as usual about this time at night I
start making uh mistakes and I was just
about to make a mistake but I caught
myself what are these eyes do you
remember they're the one particle state
the ones which look like
this s 1 S 2 S three S four and s five
and so forth they are a complete the
energy igen states they are a complete
set of States if I take all the signs
that can fit into here for example s of
x s of 2x s of 3x s of 4X that's a
complete set of
States each one of these eyes here is a
state whose wave function
is
SII but the sis are a complete set of
states and so it follows that this
expression here is just the unit
operator this is true for any complete
basis of states and go back to your
quantum mechanics and you'll remember
what this means
now that means there's a little bit of
trickery but there's nothing deep going
on here the sum of I of I
I that's an operator that's a unit
operator it's trivial it's a unit
operator and what happens if I apply it
to a state in which the particle is
known to be at x what do I get I get a
particle at X I've done nothing I've
just Rewritten the particle at position
X on the other hand what is this object
over
here
coefficient well it's a coefficient all
right but it's also a wave function do I
have it yes it's a wave function it's
the wave
function of the state
I the inner product of a particle at x
with the state Vector I is just is it s
or is it s star anybody know I know
happens to be S star happens to be
SAR so this can also be written as the
sum of
I
SAR of I of
x times the state
I that's a particle located at point x
now let me slow down here
and get any question about about this
because I'm sure this must be a little
bit
confusing this is the unit operator we
apply it on a State located at X and it
gives us a State located at X on the
other hand this inner product of a
particle at x with the wave function s
or the state Vector s is just SAR of I
it's just a wave
function
okay but what about this
what about the state
here that state is a one particle is one
particle with wave function SII I can
write it another way I can write it
another way I can write it as
follows
I is
equal to a + r y on the vacuum the
vacuum has no particles in
it if I create a particle in the state I
then indeed I have a particle at I I
have a particle in the state I so I can
substitute for this I can substitute
A+
I on the vacuum
power no one
particle one particle this is one
particle in the state
I that's all just one
particle
okay and it gives me a particle at
position
X but wait a second the thing that I
wrote down
here is exactly the quantum field side
dagger so we can now write this in
another form we can write a particle at
position
X is s
dagger at position
X on the
vacuum so now we know what side dagger
is it's an operator which creates a
particle at position
X if we have no particles and we want to
create a particle we want to change the
number of particles by adding one at
position
X then the way to do it is to apply side
dagger to the vacuum creates a particle
at position
x what if we wanted to create another
particle at position y well it's not too
hard to work out but what do you expect
you
expect just hit it with the field
operator we call this the field operator
now or the creation the the the field
operator
um we just hit it with another side
dagger but at position
y so whatever the state is if you want
to add a particle at a particular
location that's the job of the quantum
field it's a function of X Y no not why
who it's a function of X because
it has to know where to put the
particle uh it's an operator that puts a
particle at X it's not the particle the
operator that puts the particle at y so
it must be itself a function of X that's
what in a simple situation in the simple
situation that we're working on now
that's the meaning of the quantum field
it creates a
particle at position X the creation and
Annihilation operators create
particles in the energy IG
States
you
apply a dagger to the vacuum and you get
a particle not at position I that
doesn't mean anything but in the wave
function i s signs and cosiness and so
forth that's the meaning of A+ on the
other hand when you combine them
together into the quantum field the
quantum field creates a particle at
position X
what do you yeah what do you think the
annihilation op what do you think the
other piece
does that removes a particle at X if
there's one there what if there's none
there then it annihilates the
state so side dagger creates a particle
at position X whether or not there's one
there SII annihilates a particle at X or
gives zero if there's no particle there
question
please where is the information what
kind of particle could be created
barried in it should be in the little A+
but first of all yeah first of all we're
talking about bosons if you get firion
you don't do them this way which both
right there's a separate Quantum field
for each species of
Bon so what kind of boson are there in
the world there's
photons there's
gravitons there are higs bosons there
are
gluons for each species of boson there
is a separate Quantum field that creates
that kind of
particle in this
manner
right so the the particle is being
created with a Delta function
probability distribution by S of X
that's right right that's exactly right
so right excuse me
so if there's nothing if there's no
particle at a position X then s of X
does nothing no it it gives zero what
what do give zero mean the same thing
that when when an Annihilation operator
hits a state with no particle in it or
when the annihilation operator hits the
the ground state gives zero it's doing
nothing no it's giving zero zero
thinking of it in terms of particles and
positions if there's nothing at that
position to give zero to a to a position
I guess you started with a vacuum the
vacuum is not zero the vacuum is a state
it's a normalized state whose length is
one it's a good State it's there's
nothing wrong with it it's there it's a
but it it has
properties the properties are those of
empty space when an Annihilation
operator hits it it literally gives zero
the zero Vector the vector of zero
length no I don't understand what that
is
how can you have a zero zero is the
unique and only Vector that if you add
it to any other Vector you get the same
one
back it's a vector in a vector space go
back to Vector spaces Vector spaces have
in them zero
vectors zero
vectors are vectors of zero
length um it's not interesting it
doesn't have any properties it's just a
it doesn't describe doesn't describe
anything doesn't describe physically the
thing doesn't describe physically
anything it's just you add vacuum you
get something else H said if you add the
zero uh state to the vacuum get the same
thing what if you add the vacuum oh
don't you certainly don't get the if you
add the
vacuum let's say to a one particle State
then you get a state which has let's say
you add it with equal coefficients just
to be simple then you get a state that
has a prob probility of a half of having
a particle and a probability of half not
having a
particle you see the um if you add the
zero State not the vacuum to a one
particle State you just get the one
particle state if you add the vacuum to
the one particle State you get something
that has a statistical probability of
let's say a half to have a particle and
a statistical probability to not have a
particle
zero zero cannot be normalized it is
definitely not normalized it's a zero
length the one thing that you can't
normalize is a vector of zero length
right the vacuum is not a vector of zero
length it uh for a little bit of time
people generally get confused by the
notation this looks like it's zero but
it's not zero it's just a name the zero
here does not mean that it's a vector of
of zero length it does not mean that if
you add it to another Vector you get
back the same Vector it's just the name
of the vector and it represents a
perfectly good physical state it happens
to be a state with no particles in it
but it's a state it's empty space but
it's a state so we could have put a half
in there you could you could have called
it
um right you know could have called it
George Bush or whatever you want to call
it it doesn't matter
[Music]
we won't talk about annihilation of
George Bush in the yeah once that's
right once you've annihilated it you
can't put anything back right it's just
it's just zero it's literally zero right
right any operator that acts on the Zero
Vector just gives back the zero Vector
doesn't give anything
interesting right you know it's like 1
minus one is zero
take any vector and subtract it from the
same vector and you get zero uh if you
add zero to any number you get the same
number add the vector zero to
here here's the zero Vector right there
has no
length the vacuum on the other hand has
a length of one as a vector in the
vector space
normalized not easy not easy
not easy but you get used to
it um on the left board the lower sum
yeah uh does the order of those
operators no no no this only this is an
operator at each point x this is just an
ordinary number doesn't matter which
order you put it
in numbers times operators or operators
times numbers right so just think of s
of X as a collection of numbers one for
each X
all right comp H complex numers in
general complex numbers yeah yeah there
will in general be complex numbers uh
that of course depends on the solutions
to the Schrodinger equation whether it's
real or complex but that's right yeah I
take this to me that the the quantum
field description of a particle is you
basically do a creation operator on the
vacuum space how would you define a
second particle by applying
again
another you want to put a particle in
position y on top of
this
yeah
yeah if you wanted to put another
particle at position
y okay let's make a two- particle State
good let's make a two- particle State
and make and one more observation about
it here's a two particle state
this is a particle at X and a particle
at
y now X and Y could be the same point or
they could be different points right let
me point one thing out one interesting
fact um the size are made out of
annihilation operation
there are no creation operators in here
at
all every Annihilation operator commutes
with every other Annihilation
operator wait the side dagger a
creation
no I'm sorry did I make a mistake yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah right sagger is a
creation operator of course um but still
it's true that every creation but this
is the important thing it wasn't whether
it was creation or Annihilation each one
commutes with every other
one okay every create every operator in
here
creates every operator in here commutes
with every operator in here that means
side Dagger of Y and side Dagger of X
commute let's call this the state with a
particle at Y and X
well this is also equal
to side Dagger of
X Time s of
Y on
o dagger thank you I'm losing it and
that's equal to the state with a
particle at X and a particle at
y notice they're equal to each other
they equal
as a consequence of the fact that these
commute all right the fact that these
commute because they're built out of
oscillators in a certain way tells us
that it doesn't matter which order we
put the part which order we write the
particles in here in other words
particle 1 at y particle 2 at X is the
same as particle one at X particle 2 at
y That's the defining property of Bans
that it doesn't matter which order you
express them a particle particle Harry
over here and Jeffrey over here is the
same as Jeffrey over here and uh Harry
over there so that's fully equivalent to
symmetrization that's fully equivalent
to symmetrization and it tells you that
the particles are most definitely
bosons so I didn't have I didn't really
have to say from the beginning well
we're going to study bosons I could have
started with this construction and we
would have derived that the particles
studied this way are bosons so the
interesting question is well how the
hell then do you make
firion yeah that's more abstract so so
does this imply that X and Y are the
same kind of Bon X and Y X and Y are
positions yeah yeah yeah they're the
same kind of bosons that's right they're
the same kind of bons right so a given
Quantum field describes one type of
particle there's a quantum field for
photons well actually there are two
Quantum fields for photons because of
the two
polarizations there's a Quantum field
let's say a photons along some axis
there's a Quantum field for the photons
uh polarized one way another quantum
field for the photons polarize the other
way there's a Quantum field for um for
each different type of
particle there's a separate Quantum
field and if you want to make that kind
of particle you apply that Quantum field
so that's what a Quantum field
is or at least in its
simplest Incarnation and I assure you
this is the
simplest but
um the basic concept or the connection
you see what we're doing is we're
talking about the connection between
particles and
Fields here is the connection between
particles and Fields this is a field
when you apply it to the vacuum you
create a
particle you define the field to be this
you define yes that's right we defined
it but once we've defined it it's an
operator if we add it to its complex
conjugate it's a hermiss operator Herm
Mission operators are observables all of
a sudden it takes on a life as something
that we can
measure uh and uh do all the things with
observables that we do so do all the
properties of fields come out of these
creation and Annihilation operators like
yes yes none of this would be
interesting if we were talking about a
situation where you could not create and
annihilate
particles the whole point of this well I
I take I take let me say a little less
uh strongly none of this would be
interesting if we were only working in a
context where there were 37 particles
never 36 never 45 but 37 particles end
of story we wouldn't do this uh if we're
interested in studying the whole set of
possibilities of any number of particles
then this is a good tool but even better
when we're studying the possibility of
the number of particles itself being
ambiguous meaning to say a statistical
variable a quantum mechanical variable
we can study States in which there's a
superposition of different numbers of
particles no particle one particle two
particles and these have real meaning an
electromagnetic wave a laser wave is
like that a laser
wave uh is not a definite number of
particles it's a superp position 1 2 3 0
1 2 3 and uh good okay now we're
finished for
tonight for more please visit us at
stanford.edu